<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The contented cuckold, or Patience upon force is a medcine [sic] for a mad man. You batchellors both young and old give ear unto this ditty, a story here I will unfold in mirth I hope it will ... ye, a batchellor of three score years a damsel young did marry now he complains she doth him wrong and basely doth miscarry. Near Worksworth town in Darby-shire this couple they do dwell, with patience pray this ditty hear and then I bid farewell. To the tune, She cannot hold her legs together.</title>
            <author>T. R.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666-1670?</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R79</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide EBB65H[35]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99887058</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99887058</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181785</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05117)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181785)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A2:3[35])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The contented cuckold, or Patience upon force is a medcine [sic] for a mad man. You batchellors both young and old give ear unto this ditty, a story here I will unfold in mirth I hope it will ... ye, a batchellor of three score years a damsel young did marry now he complains she doth him wrong and basely doth miscarry. Near Worksworth town in Darby-shire this couple they do dwell, with patience pray this ditty hear and then I bid farewell. To the tune, She cannot hold her legs together.</title>
                  <author>T. R.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (woodcuts).  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Passenger at the three bibles on London-bridge.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[between 1666-1670]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse: "You young men all to you I call ..."</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University, Houghton Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb facs="tcp:181785:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
            <head>The Contented Cuckold, or Patience upon force is a Medcine for a Mad Man.</head>
            <argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>You batchellors both young and old</l>
                  <l>give ear unto this ditty,</l>
                  <l>A ſtory here I will unfold</l>
                  <l>in mirth I hope it will fit ye,</l>
                  <l>A batchellor of threeſſcore years</l>
                  <l>a Damſel young did marry</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now he complains ſhe doth him wrong</l>
                  <l>and baſely doth miſcarry:</l>
                  <l>Near <hi>Workſworth</hi> Town in <hi>Darby-ſhire</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>this couple they do dwell,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>With patience pray this ditty hear</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>and then I bid farewell.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </argument>
            <opener>To the Tune, <hi>She cannot hold her Legs together.</hi>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>YOu young Men all to you I call</l>
               <l>whether you live in Town or City,</l>
               <l>A Warning take by this my fall</l>
               <l>which I ſhall declare in this my ditty</l>
               <l>When as you do a Wooing go</l>
               <l>pray have a care you be not ſcorned,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>For if fortune ſay it muſt be ſo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>you ſoon may come for to be horned.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Batchellor full thréeſcore years</l>
               <l>I lived long in joy and pleaſure,</l>
               <l>I was quite bid of grief and cares</l>
               <l>I had houſe &amp; Land &amp; ſtore of Treaſure,</l>
               <l>I did provide Mony to hide,</l>
               <l>at laſt blind Cupid he me Wounded,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>With a <unclear>dart</unclear> of Love but now I can prove</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>my heart with grief is almoſt drown did.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then to Cupids Court I did reſort</l>
               <l>and there I met with Venus Siſter,</l>
               <l>Full thréeſcore pound a true report</l>
               <l>I gave for <hi>Mally</hi> would God I had miſt her</l>
               <l>To make her gay I ſlung away</l>
               <l>full ten pound more to buy her cloathing</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>Still my Eſtate goes to decay</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>for to Cuckold me ſhe counts it nothing.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All <hi>Darby-ſhire</hi> could not compare</l>
               <l>with pritty <hi>Mally</hi> for Wit and beauty</l>
               <l>I thought ſhe was a Jewell rare</l>
               <l>which made me dote in love and duty</l>
               <l>With a Forehead high and Rouling eye</l>
               <l>which ſignifies that ſhe loves ſporting,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>She ſcorns with me <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ow for to lye</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>but to. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>A Young Man living in the Town</l>
               <l>has ſtollen from me her love &amp; duty,</l>
               <l>No comfort I get but a frown</l>
               <l>not ſcarce a look upon her beauty:</l>
               <l>For all her delight both day and night</l>
               <l>is in his company for ſporting</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>The boys cry Cockoo in my ſight</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>for to Cuckold me ſhe counts it nothing.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My aged looks ſhe doth diſdain</l>
               <l>with taunts and fears I now am ſcorned</l>
               <l>My bed likewiſe ſhe doth refrain</l>
               <l>by <hi>Dick</hi> it is I muſt be horned,</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Mary</hi> ſhe abuſeth me</l>
               <l>which makes my friends to fear &amp; ſcoff me</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>And the boys cry Cuckoo in my ſight</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>becauſe <hi>Dick</hi> doth make a Cukold of me</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My means they Waſt both night and day</l>
               <l>moſt wilfully without all meaſure</l>
               <l>My Goods and Cattle is their prey</l>
               <l>they ſéek all means to Waſt my treaſure</l>
               <l>While they do Sing my hands I Wring</l>
               <l>which makes my friends to fear &amp; ſcoff me</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>And the boys, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now may I ſigh lament and mourn</l>
               <l>I do confeſs it was my folly,</l>
               <l>Now I may I ſit like an idle drone</l>
               <l>or like one ſtruck in a Melancholly,</l>
               <l>While <hi>Mary and Dick</hi> doth play the trick</l>
               <l>of Put In, Or elſe get of me,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>In houſe or barn if weather warm</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>there Dick muſt make a Cuckold of me.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus night and day they ſpend away</l>
               <l>their time in this unlawful carriage,</l>
               <l>Which makes me cry as well I may,</l>
               <l>to curſe the day and time of Marriage</l>
               <l>My Garments bare and my White Hair</l>
               <l>and my Fore-man with her is ſcorned,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>The boys cryes Cuckoo to my face</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>and ſays that Dick my head has horned</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You Batchellors and married men</l>
               <l>whether you live in Town or City,</l>
               <l>Let me intreat you once again</l>
               <l>to read this harmleſs ditty,</l>
               <l>No harm at all is in this Wall</l>
               <l>For all poor <hi>Robin</hi> now is ſcorned,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pray do not fear at Robin here</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>you know not who may next be horned.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now the Proverb old I think upon</l>
               <l>ſayes a Cuckold is a good mans fellow</l>
               <l>My time is ſpent I muſt be gone</l>
               <l>come fill's a cup of Ale that's mellow</l>
               <l>For <hi>Mal</hi> and <hi>Dick</hi> will play the trick</l>
               <l>of Put In, Or elſe get of me,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>In houſe or barn &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now to conclude and make an end</l>
               <l>hoping I have no Man offended,</l>
               <l>Nor yet done wrong to any friend</l>
               <l>he that thinks ſo pray let him mend it,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Dick</hi> will play the trick</l>
               <l>of Put In, Or elſe get of me,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>And the boys cry Cuckoo to my face</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>becauſe Dick doth make a Cuckold of me.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. R.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed for Thomas Paſſenger at the three bibles on London-bridge.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
